In this video, I'd like to
在这段视频中 我想
tell you how to write
告诉你怎样
control statements for your
为你的 Octave 程序写控制语句
Octave programs, so things
诸如
like "for", "while" and "if" statements
"for" "while" "if" 这些语句
and also how to define and use functions.
并且如何定义和使用方程
Here's my Octave window. Let
这是我们的 Octave 窗口
me first show you how to use a "for" loop.
我先告诉你如何使用 “for” 循环
I'm going to start by setting v
首先 我要将 v 值设为
to be a 10 by
一个10行1列
1 vector 0.
的零向量
Now, here's I write
现在 我要写一个 “for" 循环
a "for" loop for I equals 1 to 10.
让 i 等于 1 到 10
That's for I equals Y colon 10.
写出来就是 i = 1:10
And let's see, I'm
让我们来看看
going to set V of I
我要设 v(i) 的值
equals two to the
等于 2 的 i 次方
power of I, and finally
循环最后
end.
记得写上“end”
The white space does not matter,
这里的空格没关系
so I am putting the spaces
所以我就加一些空格
just to make it look nicely indented,
让缩进后的代码看起来结构更清晰
but you know spacing doesn't matter.
但是你要知道这里的空格没有意义
But if I do this, then the
如果按我这样做 那么
result is that V gets
向量 v 的值就是
set to, you know, two to
这样一个集合 2的一次方
the power one, two to the power two, and so on.
2的二次方 依此类推
So this is syntax for I
于是这就是我的 i 等于 1 到 10
equals one colon 10 that
的语句结构
makes I loop through the
让 i 遍历 1 到 10
values one through 10.
的值
And by the way, you can also do
另外 你还可以通过
this by setting your
设置你的 indices (索引) 等于 1
indices equals one to
一直到10
10, and so the
来做到这一点
indices in the array from one to 10.
这时 indices 就是一个从1到10的序列
You can also write for I equals indices.
你也可以写 i = indices
And this is actually the same as if I equals one to 10.
这实际上和我直接把 i 写到 1 到 10 是一样
You can do, you know, display
你可以写 disp(i)
I and this would do the same thing.
也能得到一样的结果
So, that is a "for" loop,
所以 这就是一个 “for” 循环
if you are familiar with "break"
如果你对 “break” 和 “continue” 语句比较熟悉
and "continue", there's "break" and
Octave里也有 “break” 和 “continue” 语句
"continue" statements, you can
你也可以在 Octave环境里
also use those inside loops
使用那些循环语句
in octave, but first
但是首先让我告诉你
let me show you how a while loop works.
一个 while 循环是如何工作的
So, here's my vector
这是我的 v 向量
V. Let's write the while loop.
让我们写个 while 循环
I equals 1, while I
i = 1 ;
is less than or equal to
while i <= 5 ;
5, let's set
让我们设置
V I equals one hundred
v(i) 等于 100
and increment I by
然后 i 加 1
one, end.
结束 (end)
So this says what?
所以这是什么意思呢
I starts off equal to
我让 i 取值从 1 开始
one and then I'm going
然后我要
to set V I equals one
让 v(i) 等于 100
hundred and increment I by
再让 i 递增 1
one until I is, you know, greater than five.
直到 i 大于 5停止
And as a result of that,
现在来看一下结果
whereas previously V was this powers of two vector.
原来的向量 v 是2的这些次方
I've now taken the first
我现在已经取出了
five elements of my vector
向量的前五个元素
and overwritten them with this value one hundred.
把他们用100覆盖掉
So that's a syntax for a while loop.
这就是一个while循环的句法结构
Let's do another example.
现在我们来分析另外一个例子
Y equals one while
i = 1; while true,
true and here
这里我将向你展示
I wanted to show you how to use a break statement.
如何使用break语句
Let's say V I equals 999
比方说 v(i) = 999
and I equals i+1
然后让 i = i+1
if i equals 6 break and
当 i 等于6的时候 break (停止循环)
end.
结束 (end)
And this is also our first
当然这也是我们第一次
use of an if statement, so
使用一个 if 语句 所以
I hope the logic of this makes sense.
我希望你们可以理解这个逻辑
Since I equals one and, you know, increment loop.
让 i 等于1 然后开始下面的增量循环
While repeatedly set V I equals 1
while语句重复设置 v(i) 等于1 (此处口误 应为999 译者注)
and increment i by 1,
不断让i增加
and then when 1 i
然后当 i 达到6
gets up to 6, do a
做一个
break which breaks here although
中止循环的命令
the while do and so, the
尽管有while循环 语句也就此中止
effective is should be to take
所以最后的效果是
the first five elements of this
取出向量 v 的前5个元素
vector V and set them to 999.
并且把它们设置为999
And yes, indeed, we're taking
然后运行 的确如此
V and overwritten the first five elements with 999.
我们用999覆盖了 v 的前五个元素
So, this is the
所以 这就是
syntax for "if" statements, and
if 语句和 while 语句的句法结构
for "while" statement, and notice the end.
并且要注意 要有end
We have two ends here.
这里是有两个 end 的
This ends here ends the if statement
这里的 end 结束的是 if 语句
and the second end here ends the while statement.
第二个 end 结束的是 while 语句
Now let me show you the more general syntax for
现在让我告诉你使用 if-else 语句时
how to use an if-else statement.
更一般的句法结构
So, let's see, V 1
举个例子 v(1)
is equal to 999, let's
等于999 假设我们
type V1 equals to 2 for this example.
令 v(1) 等于2
So, let me type
所以 让我输入
if V 1 equals 1 display the value as one.
if v(1) == 1, disp('The value is one');
Here's how you write an else
这里出现了一个else语句
statement, or rather here's an
或者更确切地说 这里是一个
else if: V 1 equals
elseif语句 elseif v(1) == 2,
2. This is, if in case that's true in our example, display
这就是说 如果这种情况下命题为真
the value as 2, else
执行 disp('The value is two');
display, the value is not one or two.
否则(else) 执行 disp('The value is not one or two');
Okay, so that's a  if-else
好了 这就是一个if-else语句
if-else statement it ends.
if-else语句 记得最后有end
And of course, here we've just
当然了 我们刚刚设置过
set v 1 equals 2, so hopefully, yup,
v(1)等于2 所以显然
displays that the value is 2.
显示的是 "The value is two"
And finally, I don't
最后 我觉得现在
think I talked about this earlier, but
提醒一件事
if you ever need to exit Octave,
如果你需要退出 Octave
you can type the exit command and
你可以键入 exit 命令然后
you hit enter that will cause Octave
回车就会退出 Octave
to quit or the 'q'--quits
或者命令 ‘quit’
command also works.
也可以
Finally, let's talk about
最后 让我们来说说
functions and how to define
函数 (functions)
them and how to use them.
如何定义和调用函数
Here's my desktop, and I
这是我的桌面
have predefined a file
我在桌面上存了一个
or pre-saved on my desktop a file called "squarethisnumber.m".
预先定义的文件 名为 “squarethisnumber.m”
This is how you define functions in Octave.
这就是在 Octave 环境下定义的函数
You create a file called, you know,
你需要创建一个文件
with your function name and then ending in .m,
用你的函数名来命名 然后以 .m 的后缀结尾
and when Octave finds
当 Octave 发现这文件
this file, it knows that this
它知道应该在什么位置
where it should look for the definition of the function "squarethisnumber.m".
寻找 squareThisNumber.m 这个函数的定义
Let's open up this file.
让我们打开这个文件
Notice that I'm using the
请注意 我使用的是
Microsoft program Wordpad to open up this file.
微软的写字板程序来打开这个文件
I just want to encourage you, if
我只是想建议你
your using Microsoft Windows, to
如果你也使用微软的 Windows 系统
use Wordpad rather than
那么可以使用写字板程序
Notepad to open up these
而不是记事本 来打开这些文件
files, if you have a
如果你有别的什么
different text editor that's fine
文本编辑器 那也可以
too, but notepad sometimes messes up the spacing.
但记事本有时会把代码的间距弄得很乱
If you only have Notepad, that should
如果你只有记事本程序
work too, that could work
那也能用
too, but if you
但最好是
have Wordpad as well, I
如果你有写字板的话
would rather use that or some
我建议你用写字板
other text editor, if you have a different text editor for editing your functions.
或者其他可以编辑函数的文本编辑器
So, here's how you define the function in Octave.
现在我们来说如何在 Octave 里定义函数
Let me just zoom in a little bit.
我们先来放大一点
And this file has just three lines in it.
这个文件只有三行
The first line says function Y equals square root
第一行写着 function y = squareThisNumber(x)
number of X, this tells
这就告诉 Octave
Octave that I'm gonna return
我想返回一个 y 值
the value Y, I'm gonna
我想返回一个值
return one value and that
并且返回的这个值
the value is going to
将被存放于
be saved in the variable Y
变量 y 里
and moreover, it tells Octave
另外 它告诉了 Octave
that this function has one argument,
这个函数有一个参数
which is the argument X,
就是参数 x
and the way the function
还有定义的函数体
body is defined, if Y equals X squared.
也就是 y 等于 x 的平方
So, let's try to call
现在让我们尝试调用这个函数
this function "square", this number
SquareThisNumber(5)
5, and this actually
这实际上
isn't going to work, and
是行不通的
Octave says square this number it's undefined.
Octave 说这个方程未被定义
That's because Octave doesn't know where to find this file.
这是因为 Octave 不知道在哪里找这个文件
So as usual, let's use PWD,
所以像之前一样 我们??使用 pwd
or not in my directory,
现在不在我的目录下
so let's see this c:\users\ang\desktop.
因此我们把路径设为 "C:\User\ang\desktop"
That's where my desktop is.
这就是我的桌面的路径
Oops, a little typo there.
噢 打错了
Users ANG desktop
应该是 "Users"
and if I now type square
现在如果我
root number 5, it returns the
键入SquareThisNumber(5)
answer 25.
返回值是25
As kind of an advanced feature, this
还有一种更高级的功能
is only for those of you
这只是对那些知道
that know what the term search path means.
“search path (搜索路径)” 这个术语的人使用的
But so if you
所以如果你
want to modify the Octave
想要修改 Octave
search path and you
的搜索路径
could, you just think of
你可以把下面这部分
this next part as advanced
作为一个进阶知识
or optional material.
或者选学材料
Only for those who are either
仅适用于那些
familiar with the concepts of
熟悉编程语言中
search paths and permit languages,
搜索路径概念的同学
but you can use the
你可以使用
term addpath, safety colon,
addpath 命令添加路径
slash users/ANG/desktop to
添加路径 “C:\Users\ang\desktop”
add that directory to the
将该目录添加到
Octave search path so that
Octave 的搜索路径
even if you know, go to
这样即使你跑到
some other directory I can
其他路径底下
still, Octave still knows
Octave依然知道
to look in the users ANG
会在 Users\ang\desktop
desktop directory for functions
目录下寻找函数
so that even though I'm in
这样 即使我现在
a different directory now, it still
在不同的目录下 它仍然
knows where to find the square this number function.
知道在哪里可以找到 “SquareThisNumber” 这个函数
Okay?
OK
But if you're not familiar
但是 如果你不熟悉
with the concept of search path, don't worry
搜索路径的概念
about it.
不用担心
Just make sure as you use
只要确保
the CD command to go to
在执行函数之前 先用 cd 命令
the directory of your function before
设置到你函数所在的目录下
you run it and that actually works just fine.
实际上也是一样的效果
One concept that Octave has
Octave 还有一个
that many other programming
其他许多编程语言都没有的概念
languages don't is that it
那就是它可以
can also let you define
允许你定义一个函数
functions that return multiple values or multiple arguments.
使得返回值是多个值或多个参数
So here's an example of that.
这里就是一个例子
Define the function called square
定义一个函数叫
and cube this number X
“SquareAndCubeThisNumber(x)” (x的平方以及x的立方)
and what this says is this
这说的就是
function returns 2 values, y1 and y2.
函数返回值是两个 y1 和 y2
When I set down, this
接下来就是
follows, y1 is squared, y2 is execute.
y1是被平方后的数 y2是被立方后的结果
And what this does is this really returns 2 numbers.
这就是说 函数会真的返回2个值
So, some of you depending
所以 有些同学可能会根据
on what programming language you use,
你使用的编程语言
if you're familiar with, you know, CC++ your offer.
比如你们可能熟悉的C或C++
Often, we think of the function as return in just one value.
通常情况下 认为作为函数返回值只能是一个值
But just so the syntax in Octave
但 Octave 的语法结构就不一样
that should return multiple values.
可以返回多个值
Now back in the Octave window. If
现在回到 Octave 窗口
I type, you know, a, b equals
如果我键入
square and cube this
[a,b] = SquareAndCubeThisNumber(5)
number 5 then
然后
a is now equal to
a 就等于25
25 and b is equal to
b 就等于
the cube of 5 equal to 125.
5的立方 125
So, this is often
所以说如果你需要定义一个函数
convenient if you needed to define
并且返回多个值
a function that returns multiple values.
这一点常常会带来很多方便
Finally, I'm going to show
最后 我来给大家演示一下
you just one more sophisticated example of a function.
一个更复杂一点的函数的例子
Let's say I have a data set
比方说 我有一个数据集
that looks like this, with data points at 1, 1, 2, 2, 3, 3.
像这样 数据点为[1,1], [2,2], [3,3]
And what I'd like
我想做的事是
to do is to define an
定义一个 Octave 函数来计算代价函数 J(θ)
octave function to compute the cost
就是计算
function J of theta for different values of theta.
不同 θ 值所对应的代价函数值 J
First let's put the data into octave.
首先让我们把数据放到 Octave 里
So I set my design
我把我的矩阵设置为
matrix to be 1,1,1,2,1,3.
X = [1 1; 1 2; 1 3];
So, this is my design
这就是我的设计矩阵 X
matrix x with x0, the
第一列表示x0项
first column being the said
矩阵的第一列
term and the second term being
第二列表示
you know, my the x-values of my three training examples.
我的三个训练样本的 x 值
And let me set
现在我再来
y to be 1-2-3 as
设置 y 值为 [1; 2; 3]
follows, which were the y axis values.
就像这样 是y轴对应值
So let's say theta
现在我们设定 theta
is equal to 0 semicolon 1.
为 [0;1]
Here at my desktop, I've
现在我的桌面上
predefined does cost function
已经有我预定义的代价函数 J
j and if I
如果我打开函数
bring up the definition of that function it looks as follows.
函数的定义应该是下面这样的
So function j equals cost function
所以 函数J 就写成
j equals x y
J = costFunctionJ(X, y, theta)
theta, some commons, specifying
这里有一些注释
the inputs and then
主要用于解释输入变量
vary few steps set m
接下来几步
to be the number trading examples
设定 m 为训练样本的数量
thus the number of rows in x.
也就是 X 的行数
Compute the predictions, predictions equals
计算预测值 predictions
x times theta and so
预测值等于 X 乘以 theta
this is a common that's wrapped
这里是注释行
around, so this is probably the preceding comment line.
是上一个注释行拐过来的部分
Computer script errors by, you know, taking
下面就是计算平方误差 公式就是
the difference between your predictions and
预测值减去 y 值
the y values and taking the
然后取出来每一项进行平方
element of y squaring and then
最后就可以
finally computing the cost
计算代价函数 J
function J. And Octave knows
并且 Octave 知道
that J is a value I
J 是一个我想返回的值
want to return because J appeared here in the function definition.
因为 J 出现在了我函数的定义里
Feel free by the way to pause
另外 你可以随时
this video if you want
暂停一下视频
to look at this function
如果你想
definition for longer and
仔细看一下这个函数的定义
kind of make sure that you understand the different steps.
确保你明白了定义中的每一步
But when I run it in
现在当我
Octave, I run j equals
在 Octave 里运行时
cost function j x y theta.
我键入 j = costFunctionJ(x, y, theta)
It computes. Oops, made a typo there.
然后他就开始计算 噢 又打错了
It should have been capital X. It
这里应该是大写 X
computes J equals 0 because
它就计算出 j 等于0
if my data set was,
这是因为 如果我的数据集
you know, 123, 123 then setting, theta 0
x 为 [1;2;3] y 也为 [1;2;3] 然后设置 θ0 等于0
equals 0, theta 1 equals
θ1 等于1
1, this gives me exactly the
这给了我恰好45度的斜线
45-degree line that fits my data set perfectly.
这条线是可以完美拟合我的数据集的
Whereas in contrast if I set
而相反地 如果我设置
theta equals say 0, 0,
theta 等于[0; 0]
then this hypothesis is
那么这个假设就是
predicting zeroes on everything
0是所有的预测值
the same, theta 0 equals 0,
和刚才一样 设置θ0 = 0
theta 1 equals 0 and
θ1 也等于0
I compute the cost function
然后我计算的代价函数
then it's 2.333 and that's
结果是2.333
actually equal to 1 squared,
实际上 他就等于1的平方
which is my squared error on
也就是第一个样本的平方误差
the first example, plus 2 squared,
加上2的平方
plus 3 squared and then
加上3的平方
divided by 2m, which is
然后除以2m
2 times number of training examples,
也就是训练样本数的两倍
which is indeed 2.33 and
这就是2.33
so, that sanity checks that
因此这也反过来验证了
this function here is, you
我们这里的函数
know, computing the correct cost
计算出了正确的代价函数
function and these are the couple examples
这些就是我们
we tried out on our
用简单的训练样本
simple training example.
尝试的几次试验
And so that sanity tracks
这也可以作为我们对
that the cost function J,
定义的代价函数 J
as defined here, that it
进行了完整性检查
is indeed, you know, seeming to compute
确实是可以计算出正确的代价函数的
the correct cost function, at least
至少基于这里的 X
on our simple training set
和 y 是成立的
that we had here with X
也就是我们
and Y being this
这几个简单的训练集
simple training example that we solved.
至少是成立的
So, now you know how
好啦 现在你知道
to right control statements like for loops,
如何在 Octave 环境下写出正确的控制语句
while loops and if statements
比如 for 循环、while 循环和 if 语句
in octave as well as how to define and use functions.
以及如何定义和使用函数
In the next video, I'm
在接下来的视频中
going to just very quickly
我会非常快的
step you through the logistics
介绍一下
of working on and
如何在这门课里
submitting problem sets for
完成和提交作业
this class and how to use our submission system.
如何使用我们的提交系统
And finally, after that, in
在此之后
the final octave tutorial video,
在最后的 Octave 教程视频里
I wanna tell you about vectorization, which
我会讲解一下向量化
is an idea for how to
这是一种可以使你的
make your octave programs run much fast.
Octave 程序运行非常快的思想(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )